Finding Aid for Rudolph E. Reichert Papers 1907-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rudolph E. Reichert Papers 1907-1962
Reichert, Rudolph E., 1887-1965.
Ann Arbor, Michigan banker and commissioner of the Michigan Banking Department during the depression. Correspondence and other papers concerning his activities as banking commissioner and officer of the Michigan Bankers Association; includes letters from Mrs. Christine Reichert to her children while touring Europe, mainly Germany, on the eve of World War II, 1939; also letters between Reichert and British manufacturer in which British-American foreign policy is discussed, 1939-1945; and photographs.
8683 Aa 2
17.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Reichert (donor no. 4127 ) in March 1964. Additional later material came from family members.
The collection is open for research.
Rudolph E. Reichert was born November 13, 1887 near Ann Arbor, Michigan. After attending public schools in Ann Arbor, he became a messenger for the Farmers & Mechanics Bank in 1904. He was associated briefly with the American Savings Bank of Lansing, then returned to Ann Arbor in 1911 to assume the position of assistant cashier and director of the German-American Savings Bank, which was later consolidated with the State Savings Bank.
In 1923, Reichert became cashier of he State Savings Bank of Ann Arbor, a position he held until 1927 when he was appointed banking commissioner of Michigan by Governor Fred W. Green. He held this position through the terms of Governors Green, Brucker, Comstock, and Fitzgerald. He served as banking commissioner during the "bank holiday" in 1932, and wrote the Reorganization Banking Law which was adopted in 1933 by Michigan and several other states to avoid recurrence of the banking crisis. He also helped to draft the congressional act that established the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.
In 1935, Reichert was elected president of the National Association of Supervisors of State Banks. In 1936, following his service as banking commissioner, Reichert returned to Ann Arbor where he became a founder and first president of the Ann Arbor Savings & Commercial Bank. He served as president until 1960 when he was name chairman of the board. He retired from that position in 1962.
In 1943, Reichert was named director of the Detroit Branch of the Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago, and he served in that capacity for six years. He also served as president of the Michigan Bankers Association 1944-1945.
Reichert died December 22, 1965.
The Reichert papers span the period 1907-1965 but bulk largest for the years 1927-1936. The collection deals with Reichert's career as Commissioner of the State Banking Department of Michigan, his activities as a local bank president in Ann Arbor, an officer in the Michigan Bankers Association, and a stockholder in the Argus Corporation. There are a few scattered items of a personal nature, in short, such personal correspondence as was handled through his business office.
The papers are rich in materials on the financial crisis in Michigan during the Great Depression when he was Banking Commissioner. Reichert was also active until the early 1950's in the framing of both state and federal legislation dealing with banks, federal deposit insurance, etc., and he carried on a full correspondence with Congressman Earl Michener and Senator Arthur Vandenberg on these legislative matters. Considerable material exists on the Michigan Bankers Association, especially for the years 1941-1944, when he was an officer of the group. There is some material on Republican party matters, but it is not very full.
Ann Arbor's business and financial life is well covered for the whole period, including material on Argus, Inc. for the post-war period. The effect of both the depression and the war on small town economic life is particularly well documented. There is an interesting series of letters, 1939-1945, between Reichert and a British rope manufacturer named Hendy, in which British and American policy in foreign affairs and the conduct of the war is argued at length.
The collection has been divided into the following series: Professional Papers; State Banking Department and related; Biographical/Personal; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Banks and banking--Michigan.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1928.; Elections--Michigan--1932.; Elections--Michigan--1934.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Germany--Description and travel.; Michigan Union.; Presidents--United States--Election--1932.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Reichert, Rudolph Edward, 1887-1965.; Royal Oak (Mich.); United States. Congress--Elections, 1934.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1952.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives.
Subjects - Visual Material:
American Bankers Association.; Ann Arbor Bank.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Banks.; Banks--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Banking.; Farmers and Mechanics Bank (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Interiors.; Michigan Bankers Association.; Office workers--1951-1960.; Reichert, Rudolph Edward, 1887-1965.
Contributors:
Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1888-1973.; Brucker, William Marion, 1894-1968.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Copeland, Royal S. (Royal Samuel), 1868-1938.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Curtis, Charles, 1860-1936.; Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Friends of the Land.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; McNamara, Robert S., 1916-2009; Meader, George, 1907-1994; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Michigan Bankers Association.; Michigan. Banking Division.; Michigan Surety Company.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946.; Olds, Ransom Eli, 1864-1950.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Reichert, Christine John.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Union Guardian Trust Company (Detroit, Mich.); United States. Congress.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Walcott, Jesse P., 1893-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Professional Papers
  - 1907-1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927-1929, 39 folders (Box 1)
  - 1930-1932, 36 folders (Box 2)
  - 1933-1936, 37 folders (Box 3)
  - 1937-July 1941, 28 folders (Box 4)
  - August 1941-August 1942, 29 folders (Box 5)
  - September 1942-July 1943, 28 folders (Box 6)
  - August 1943-May 1944, 27 folders (Box 7)
  - June 1944-November 1945, 29 folders (Box 8)
  - December 1945-1948, 32 folders (Box 9)
  - 1949-June 1950, 30 folders (Box 10)
  - July 1950-October 1951, 22 folders (Box 11)
  - November 1951-1952, 31 folders (Box 12)
  - 1953-1960, 28 folders (Box 13)
- State Banking Department and related
  - Bulletins 1920-1936 (Box 14)
  - Memoranda regarding individual banks within the state 1932-1933, 1935, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Minutes of meetings, Advisory Banking Commission, State of Michigan March 1933-December 1934 (Box 14)
  - Non-member banks re-organization (memoranda covering discussions for 1933) (Box 14)
  - Federal Deposit Insurance and Reconstruction Finance Corporation, Michigan Advisory Board 1933 (Box 14)
    memoranda, minutes of meetings, telegrams
  - Classification--Michigan Non-member banks "open," as compiled for Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago and Minneapolis August 1933 (Box 14)
  - Letters to Conservators, receivers, examiners; Instructions to conservators and receivers 1927-1935 (Box 14)
  - Preferred stock from November 6, 1933-March 21, 1935 (Box 14)
  - Report of conservators from November 10, 1933-May 29, 1935 (Box 14)
  - Memoranda from G. A. Hodson
    - "54 Bank Plan" 1933 (Box 14)
    - General 1933 (Box 14)
  - Minutes (State Committee of Depositors' Liquidating Board of RFC) (Box 15)
  - Reports on loan liquidations, etc. (Box 15)
  - Memoranda from L. M. Fenton, Reconstruction Finance Corporation 1933 (Box 15)
  - Banking Situation, reorganizations, etc. (Act 32 and 54 Bank Plan) 1933-1935 (Box 15)
  - Appointments of conservators, receivers April-December, 1934 (Box 15)
  - Minutes of Bond Department Supervisory Committee 1934-1935, 3 volumes (Box 15)
  - Volume: Letters and instructions to examiners, conservators, receivers; Special Memorandums; Governor's proclamations (Box 15)
  - Michigan Master Report; Resources, Liabilities, and Examiner's classifications January 10, 1934 (Box 15)
  - Supplemental Report to Michigan Master Report (Box 15)
  - Department Receivership Data 1934-1935 (Box 15)
  - Receivership 1934 (Box 15)
  - Conservators' Report Blank for re-opening of banks (Box 15)
  - FDIC Memoranda 1934-1935 (Box 15)
  - Memoranda on Re-organization 1934 (Box 15)
  - State Acts relating to banking (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous forms (Box 16)
  - Notes on hearings for reopening of banks (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Printed materials 1927-1935 (Box 16)
  - Desk calendars 1928-1935 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks 1931-1936, 6 volumes (Box 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 10 folders (Box 17)
    (includes clippings from later career to 1960s)
- Biographical/Personal
  - Obituary; general information (Box 18)
  - Transcript of interview about his career as bank commissioner conducted by Robert M. Warner 1965 (Box 18)
  - Reminiscences of his life circa 1964 (Box 18)
  - Letters from Christine John Reichert to children while touring Europe, mainly Germany, on the eve of World War II 1939 (Box 18)
  - Published material (convention programs, etc.) (Box 18)
- Photographs
  - Ann Arbor Bank; Farmers and Mechanics Bank (Box 18)
  - Michigan Bankers Association (Box 18)
  - Portraits of Michigan governors and other politicos; photos of RER with others (Box 18)
Selective index to correspondents and subjects
Banks and Banking--Michigan
Correspondence and other papers dealing with his career as banker, as banking commissioner, and as officer of the Michigan Bankers Association. See especially papers, Feb. 1933, on the Michigan Bank Holiday and, March 1933, for the federal bank holiday.
Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.
April 27, 1931 and Nov. 17, 1931
Bonisteel, Roscoe Osmond, 1888-1972.
Correspondence throughout.
Bowles, Chester, 1901-
March 27, 1944 (enclosed with Michener letter, March 28, 1944)
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
Nov. 21, 1934; July 29, 1942; Nov. 2, 1942; Nov. 11, 1942; Jan. 30, 1943; Feb. 23, 1943; July 23, 1947
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Feb. 17, 1928, Feb. 24, 1928, Oct. 16 1928, Oct. 18, 1928, Dec. 21, 1928, Jan. 2, 1930, Jan. 3, 1930, Nov. 10, 1930, Dec. 20, 1930, July 21, 1931, Nov. 30 1931, Sept. 2, 1942.
Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.
Draft of special message of Comstock, written by Reichert, Nov. 1933; also letters of William A. Comstock: June 28, 1934; Dec. 29, 1934; April 17, 1941; Nov. 12, 1941; July 7, 1942; Jan. 2, 1943; Nov. 11, 1947
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
April 21, 1942
Copeland, Royal S. (Royal Samuel), 1868-1938.
Sept. 30, 1930
Couzens, James, 1872-1936.
Sept. 26, 1930, Mar. 31, 1934, Apr. 10, 1934, Apr. 16, 1934, Apr. 28, 1934, May 9, 1934
Curtis, Charles, 1860-1936.
June 25, 1932
Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955.
April 8, 1949
Election of 1928
Material on the election of 1928, especially regarding Arthur Vandenberg's first campaign for the Senate
Election of 1932
Material on the election of 1932, especially in correspondence with Earl Michener.
Election of 1934
Materials on the election of 1934. See especially letter, Sept. 1934
Election of 1952.
Materials on the election of 1952. See especially letter of July 14, 1952 and July 26, 1952.
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.
Feb. 19, 1947; Aug. 18, 1947; and Mar. 18, 1949
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Dec. 10, 1929; April 1, 1930; Sept. 11, 1930; Nov. 6, 1930; Nov. 30, 1932; July 11, 1934; Nov. 14, 1934
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-
July 28, 1950
Friends of the Land.
Material, 1943, on the Friends of the Land movement.
Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.
Feb. 21, 1927; May 28, 1927; July 14, 1927; July 21, 1927; Aug. 19, 1927; Nov. 4, 1927; Dec. 30, 1927; Jan. 12, 1928; Jan. 12, 1928; Jan. 19, 1928; Jan. 21, 1928; Feb. 6, 1928; March 22, 1928; May 3, 1928; July 5, 1928; Aug. 10, 1928; Aug. 14, 1928; Aug. 25, 1928; Aug. 27, 1928; Sept. 12, 1928; Oct. 2, 1928; Dec. 14, 1928; Dec. 20, 1928; Dec. 21, 1928; May 8, 1929; Aug. 24, 1929; Nov. 21, 1929; Feb. 17, 1930; May 13, 1930; May 26, 1930; Dec. 29, 1930; Aug. 8, 1933; Aug. 3, 1934
Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-
Jan. 7, 1957; Oct. 24, 1957
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.
Feb. 5, 1943; Nov. 5, 1943
McKay, Frank D., 1883-
May 5, 1927; Oct. 4, 1927; Oct. 20, 1927; Oct. 25, 1927; Dec. 30, 1927; Jan. 3, 1928; Oct. 27, 1937; Dec. 21, 1928; Dec. 26, 1928; Jan. 24, 1929; Jan. 25, 1929; March 25, 1929; April 3, 1929; April 5, 1929; April 8, 1929; Aug. 24, 1946; Sept. 3, 1929; Christmas, 1950; Sept. 19, 1929; Dec. 13, 1951; Oct. 9, 1929; Oct. 23, 1929; Nov. 18, 1929; Dec. 20, 1929; Dec. 25, 1930; Dec. 30, 1930; Nov. 4, 1931; Dec. 15, 1942 (on his indictment); July 12, 1945
McNamara, Robert S., 1916-
Dec. 22, 1960
Meader, George, 1907-
Aug. 25, 1932, June 10, 1950, Mar. 21, 1951; June 5, 1951, Sept. 6, 1953, Sept. 29, 1953, Dec. 1, 1953
Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.
Jan. 24, 1928; Feb. 1, 1928; Feb. 6, 1928; March 21, 1928; March 26, 1928; Oct. 22, 1929; Oct. 28, 1929; Nov. 15, 1929; Nov. 25, 1929; Nov. 27, 1929; Nov. 29, 1929; Jan. 25, 1930; Jan. 29, 1930; Feb. 3, 1930; April 29, 1930; May 7, 1930; May 8, 1930; July 2, 1930; July 21, 1930; Aug. 15, 1930; Aug. 27, 1930; Sept. 2, 1930; Sept. 6, 1930; Sept. 11, 1930; Sept. 12, 1930; Sept. 16, 1930; Jan. 11, 1932; March 26, 1932; April 5, 1932; May 4, 1932; May 9, 1932; May 16, 1932; May 26, 1932; June 22, 1932; July 16, 1932; Aug. 25, 1932; Sept. 16, 1932; Dec. 1, 1932; Aug. 8, 1933; Sept. 8, 1933; Feb. 8, 1934; Nov. 14, 1934; Nov. 21, 1934; May 24, 1941; May 28, 1941; June 3, 1941; Jan. 30, 1942; Feb. 5, 1942; Feb. 28, 1942; March 11, 1942; April 27, 1942; June 18, 1942; June 20, 1942; Jan. 13, 1943; Jan. 27, 1943 [with enclosure]; March 22, 1943; Jan. 27, 1944; Feb. 14, 1944; March 21, 1944; March 28, 1944; April 1, 1944; June 13, 1944; June 21, 1944; March 20, 1946; April 3 1946; April 28, 1946; May 17, 1946; Feb. 17, 1947; Sept. 22, 1947; March 18, 1949; Aug. 16, 1949; Aug. 26, 1949; Feb. 27, 1950; March 21, 1950; March 24, 1950; March 27, 1950; April 6, 1950; April 15, 1950; May 29, 1950; June 2, 1950; July 10, 1950; Dec. 18, 1950
Michigan Bankers Association
Papers, especially 1941-1944, when Reichert was an officer and president of the association.
Michigan Surety Company.
Papers, 1940
Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946.
May 28 1941, July 28, 1941, and Oct. 17, 1941
Natural resources
material, 1943, on the Friends of the Land movement.
Olds, Ransom Eli, 1864-1950.
July 6, 1932
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-1949.
April 28, 1931
Royal Oak (Mich.)
letter, April 30, 1931, discussing the condition of a Royal Oak bank in detail.
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
June 22, 1951
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
Aug. 15, 1942
Union Guardian Trust Company (Detroit, Mich.)
Correspondence, April and May 1934, between Reichert and Senator Couzens re the Union Guardian Trust Company; see also undated letter, 1937
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Apr. 1928; May 1928, July 1928, Aug. 1928; Oct., 1928; Nov. 1928, Jan. 1929; Feb. 1929, Jan. 1930, July 1931, Aug. 1931, Jan. 1932 Sept. 1932, Feb. 1933, Apr. 1933, July 1933, Aug. 1933, Nov. 1934, Dec. 1934, July 1942, Jan. 1943, Apr. 1944 Mar. 1945, Jan. 1946, Apr. 1946, Aug. 1946, Nov. 1946, Mar. 1947, May 1947, June 1947, Mar. 1949, June 1949, Oct. 1949, Dec. 1949, Jan. 1950, July 1950
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
April 9, 1941 and Aug. 6, 1942
Walcott, Jesse P., 1893-
Nov. 27, 1946; June 27, 1947; July 2, 1947; Sept. 10, 1952; Jan. 24, 1953; March 10, 1953; April 19, 1953; Aug. 3, 1953; Aug. 13, 1953; Oct. 23, 1953